<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meld | Ambivalent Certainty]]></title>
  <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/blog/categories/meld/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-04T07:12:16+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://kaiw.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kai Willadsen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life as a GTK+ app developer]]></title>
    <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2015/01/04/life-as-a-gtk-app-developer/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-04T07:09:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2015/01/04/life-as-a-gtk-app-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The GTK+ 3 port of Meld was developed against 3.8, targetting 3.6. When I
started doing the port, 3.8 was what was available in current distributions,
so it seemed reasonable to expect that by the time the port was done, many
users would have access to it. In fact, it took way longer than I&rsquo;d hoped and
the GTK+ 3 port was released at about the same time as GTK+ 3.14 came out,
which then broke everything.</p>

<h2>GtkTextView/GtkSourceView painting</h2>

<p>Drawing in GtkTextView and GtkSourceView changed to use a new API involved
drawing of layers, and changed how the background was drawn. The new API is
actually really nice and will be great to use, but&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip;well, it broke everything. The custom painting that Meld does all over the
textview was broken, and because the background clearing was a theme-specific
change, it broke differently in different themes.</p>

<p>Oh, and don&rsquo;t worry! All of this was completely unannounced. I found out about
the layer drawing by reading a random blog post <em>after</em> the release of 3.14
mentioning that it might be useful for another application. It will be too&hellip;
one day.</p>

<h2>Images in dialogs</h2>

<p>Dialogs used to be guaranteed to have an image if a message-type was set. This
is no longer the case, so any code that assumed that there was going to be an
image there just breaks. Good job!</p>

<p>This broke lots of random dialogs in Meld, and prevented people from doing
things like&hellip; saving files.</p>

<h2>Dialogs in general</h2>

<p>Spacing, padding and outline drawing have all changed, so all our dialogs now
look awful. They&rsquo;ll have to be adjusted to look okay with GTK+ 3.14 which
will, by extension, make them look awful with everything pre-3.14.</p>

<h2>Size calculation changes</h2>

<p>In 3.10, the way GtkBox expand properties propagate changed. Now granted, it
was weirdly broken before, but this behaviour change made a couple of bits of
Meld&rsquo;s preferences dialog unusable.</p>

<h1>Life as a GTK+ app developer</h1>

<p>When Meld 3.12 was released, my plan was to get a really quick 3.14 release
done and out, and try for another quick release to sync up Meld and GNOME on
3.16. Instead, I&rsquo;ve spent most of my very limited spare time plugging holes
in various regressions.</p>

<p>Accusations that level X of a technology stack doesn&rsquo;t really understand what
it&rsquo;s like for level Y of the technology stack aren&rsquo;t exactly new. Some vocal
members of the community will complain about this in any stack, and GTK+ is
no different. However, this is the first release cycle that I&rsquo;ve spent hours
actively cursing breakages in the GTK+ stack. I hope it&rsquo;s a blip.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's new in Meld 3.12]]></title>
    <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2014/09/24/meld-3-12/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-24T07:40:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2014/09/24/meld-3-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After an unexpectedly long transition, Meld 3.12 is the first stable release
of Meld based on GTK+ 3. As usual, plenty has changed. While a lot of work
this time around was behind the scenes, some of that work has enabled cool new
features as well.</p>

<h2>Appearance</h2>

<p>Everything looks&hellip; newer. With the update to GTK+ 3, we&rsquo;ve removed the use of
some older widgets&mdash;most notably the old-style file selectors&mdash;and
somewhat modernised the layout and overall visual appearance. We&rsquo;ve also
cleaned up some icons to be a little more balanced, and updated the overall
colour scheme. While not ready yet, the next release cycle will also see
support for global dark theme settings.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/blog/3-12-theme.png" title="Theme improvements for 3.12" >
<img class="right" src="/images/blog/3-13-theme-dark.png" title="Upcoming dark theme support" ></p>

<div style="clear: both;"></div>


<p>Under GNOME Shell, Meld will integrate into the GNOME 3 style application
menu, and we&rsquo;ll fall back to adding a new &ldquo;Meld&rdquo; menu for other platforms.</p>

<h2>Comparisons</h2>

<p>Pane resizing&mdash;a long-standing feature request, finally picked up by
Marco Brito&mdash;has been merged. Hopefully this will make comparisons easier
for those of you who stuck trying to do a three-way merge on a 13" screen.</p>

<p>File comparisons now show a notification if a file is modified outside of
Meld, and prompt to reload. We also display better labels for file comparisons
launched from version control, so you should no longer see useless temporary
file names here.</p>

<p>In folder comparisons, if you have a folder that&rsquo;s empty after filtering has
been applied, that folder will (finally) be correctly trimmed from the tree.
We also now use normal desktop trash handling for file operations, instead of
just deleting things forever without warning&hellip;</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/blog/conflict-dialog.png" title="Marking conflicts resolved" ></p>

<p>On the version control side of things, we have some support for showing file
metadata, including renames thanks to Louis des Landes. Currently this is only
used by Bazaar, but we&rsquo;ll hopefully extend this support to Git and Mercurial
soon. Finally, as a handy touch, for conflict resolutions that you start from
a Meld version control tab, we now prompt to mark a conflict as resolved when
you close the file comparison.</p>

<div style="clear: both;"></div>


<h2>Help and translation</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/blog/yelp-help.png" title="Yelp browsing new Meld help" ></p>

<p>Meld now uses Mallard for documentation, and there&rsquo;s a <strike>hack</strike>
script that we use to provide <a href="http://meldmerge.org/help/">online help</a> for
non-GNOME platforms.</p>

<p>Thanks to the thoroughly awesome GNOME Translation Teams, Meld&rsquo;s translations
are <a href="https://l10n.gnome.org/module/meld/">looking good</a>, with several full
translations for the new manual as well! Of course, our translation coverage
could always be better, so if you notice gaps in your native language support,
please consider <a href="https://l10n.gnome.org/teams/">joining a team</a> to help out.</p>

<div style="clear: both;"></div>


<h2>Windows support</h2>

<p>While Meld has worked on Windows for some time, we are now building and
distributing stand-alone Windows installers for Meld. Some of our Windows
support is still a little rough around the edges, but with more users and a
better distribution story, you can expect to see this situation continue to
improve in the coming release cycles. Thanks go to Keegan Witt for maintaining
the unofficial binary distribution, and for helping out with the transition.</p>

<h2>Behind the scenes</h2>

<p>Meld is now a single-instance application, using the GtkApplication model. By
default Meld will still use multiple windows, and each command-line process
will wait until its window has closed, so from a user point of view, very
little should change.</p>

<p>With the transition to the newer GTK+ 3 platform and related tools, we&rsquo;ve also
cleaned up tonnes of unpleasant code. Preferences handling has been rewritten,
our custom colours are CSS-themed and we&rsquo;ve moved to making heavier use of the
excellent GtkSourceView library.</p>

<h2>Future plans</h2>

<p>By the time you read this, 3.12 will probably have already branched, and some
pending stuff for 3.13 will be going in. My list of things-to-merge already
includes incremental find for file comparisons, better dark theme support, and
a rework of conflict resolution mode to show a combination of the pre-merged
file with ancestor information for conflicting sections.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like to get involved with Meld development then please get in
touch on the mailing list: <a href="mailto:meld-list@gnome.org">meld-list@gnome.org</a>.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thanks to everyone who contributed to the release, whether through features,
translations or bugfixes:
Andika Triwidada, Bartosz Dziewoński, Ben Ross,
Benjamin Steinwender, Casey, Christoph Brill, Daniel Mustieles, Daniel Pantea,
Dimitris Spingos, Dominique Leuenberger, Enrico Nicoletto, Facundo Dario
Illanes, fr33domlover, Fran Diéguez, Gabor Kelemen, Gianni Trovisi, Inaki
Larranaga Murgoitio, Jiri Grönroos, Josef Andersson, Kai Willadsen, Lars
Wendler, Lasse Liehu, Louis des Landes, Marco Brito, Marek Černocký, Matej
Urbančič, Milo Casagrande, Peter Tyser, Piotr Drąg, Rafael Ferreira, Thomas
Klausner, Tom Scytale, Tom Tryfonidis, Ville-Pekka Vainio, Yuri Myasoedov,
zodiac111, Özgür Sarıer, Мирослав Николић</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meld features that people have never asked for]]></title>
    <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2014/03/29/features-people-have-never-asked-for/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-29T09:45:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2014/03/29/features-people-have-never-asked-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People ask for new features all the time. Sometimes they&rsquo;re good ideas, sometimes&hellip; they&rsquo;re not. Sometimes there&rsquo;s a better way to address the requested feature. However, to me it&rsquo;s interesting to contemplate the things that people <em>don&rsquo;t</em> ask for.</p>

<h2>New Window</h2>

<p>Meld is a single window app. It isn&rsquo;t designed that way&hellip; it&rsquo;s just that it&rsquo;s never supported anything else. No one has <em>ever</em> asked to be able to open a second window.</p>

<p>In Meld 3.11.0, we now at least have the notion of windows, though we still don&rsquo;t actually have a &lsquo;New Window&rsquo; menu item. Maybe one day&hellip;</p>

<h2>D-Bus API</h2>

<p>Meld uses D-Bus to support some very limited single-instance features; specifically, you can open a comparison in a new tab. However, no one has ever expressed any interest in having an actual D-Bus API for Meld.</p>

<h2>Move to Trash</h2>

<p>We do some really terrifying things when handling folders and directories, the most obvious being that you can recursively and permanently delete folders from within a folder comparison. Permanently deleting files doesn&rsquo;t even prompt! Despite this being a pretty nasty example of not handling user error, no one has ever suggested that maybe we should be less insane.</p>

<p>In Meld 3.11.0, we use GIO to &lsquo;trash&rsquo; things for us, which should do-the-right-thing on different platforms.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's new in Meld 1.8?]]></title>
    <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2013/09/15/meld-18/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T08:59:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2013/09/15/meld-18</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quite a bit!</p>

<p><strong>File comparisons</strong> are faster and interactivity is better while recomputing
changes, and initial support was added for comparing files using
synchronisation points.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/blog/FolderColumns.png" title="Extra columns in folder comparisons" ></p>

<p><strong>Folder comparisons</strong> now have extra columns so you can see more file information
when doing your comparison. There is also a new shallow comparison option,
speeding things up nicely for people dealing with folders full of huge files.</p>

<p><strong>Version control view</strong> has had some significant compatibility updates,
culminating in the death of the dreaded &lsquo;patch failed&rsquo; dialog, as Meld now
uses more reliable ways of interacting with version control systems. Some big
updates went in to support more commands, give better feedback, and do a
better job of launching conflict comparisons.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/blog/DarkTheme.png" title="Support for custom themes" ></p>

<p><strong>Meld</strong> also received lots of little improvements here and there. We now have
better themeability (a big deal for dark theme fans), support for relaunching
recent comparisons, and a new UI for starting comparisons. Last but not least,
Meld&rsquo;s Windows support has improved, and bundled installers are becoming
available for Windows users (thanks to Keegan Witt).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The tale of the unwatched list]]></title>
    <link href="http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2013/01/12/mailing-list/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-12T07:39:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://kaiw.github.com/blog/2013/01/12/mailing-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started maintaining Meld, a surprising number of accounts for new
<strike>chores</strike> services entered my life. Inevitably, a few
responsibilities were missed.</p>

<p>For example, until very recently, I didn&rsquo;t have admin access for the
<a href="https://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/meld-list">Meld mailing list</a>.
Since all posts to the list by non-members are held for moderation, I&rsquo;m pretty
sure that this means that all non-member list traffic over the last few years
has been dropped on the floor.</p>

<p>Whoops.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s worse is that since I&rsquo;ve started doing the moderation, there&rsquo;s been
a consistent trickle of messages needing approval. Meld&rsquo;s list doesn&rsquo;t exactly
have a lot of traffic, so an extra message every couple of days is a
significant boost.</p>

<p>&hellip;all of which makes me wonder just how many people didn&rsquo;t become involved
in Meld due to an unwatched moderation queue.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
